<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hieu's blog</title>
    <description>My blog about Linux, Database, Infrastructure, some mathematics, and mindset.</description>
    <link>https://blog.tracelog.in/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.tracelog.in/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2020 22:30:33 +0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2020 22:30:33 +0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.5.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Struggling and auditing myself in 2019</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Before you read&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I write this post only for myself in devops &amp;amp; infrastructure context, not everyone’s else issues.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And the whole thing could be very discrete, not closely related to each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;facts&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FACTS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m obsessed with keeping infrastructure up and finding better ways for commitments everyday. My mental health turns bad because of seeing fucking services/ops that &lt;strong&gt;were built &amp;amp; done carelessly&lt;/strong&gt; without any sufficiently exhausting efforts, not only from others engineers, but also &lt;strong&gt;from myself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Devops/SRE scope, trying to adapt incoming tasks, solve problems by providing commonplace solution is…easy, it’s get-shit-done inattentively, something is workaround, temporary. It’s &lt;strong&gt;EASY THINGS&lt;/strong&gt;, come with useless, low impact also very breakable. But &lt;strong&gt;good things take time and efforts&lt;/strong&gt;. And the hard things make big impact.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As a good rule of thumb, proprietary technology must be at least 10 times better than its closest substitute in some important dimension to lead to a real monopolistic advantage. - Zero to One – Peter Thiel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;max-width: 700px; vertical-align: middle; display: block; margin: auto;&quot;&gt;&lt;svg class=&quot;bar-chart&quot;&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/chart.xkcd@1/dist/chart.xkcd.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  const svg = document.querySelector('.bar-chart')

  new chartXkcd.Bar(svg, {
    title: 'RELATIVE BETWEEN VALUE &amp; DOING THINGS',
    xLabel: 'THINGS',
    yLabel: 'TIME + EFFORTS + VALUES',
    data: {
      labels: ['EASY', 'NORMAL', 'HARD'],
      datasets: [{
        data: [10, 30, 100],
      }],
    },
    options: {
      yTickCount: 6,
      dataColors: ['gray', '#bbccdd', '#ff851b']
    },
  });
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well… at some points in my work-life, I realize that issues are not from the context, not from others. &lt;a style=&quot;color:red;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mostly issues are from me&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, from my bad habits, bad thingking, bad mindsets. It makes me feel &lt;strong&gt;shutting down&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;dumb&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;fucked-up&lt;/strong&gt; also with &lt;strong&gt;getting lost&lt;/strong&gt;. I went down the wrong path many times, also got many bad results in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;color:red;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AM I UNRELIABLE?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what’s common failures that I was facing? Lesson learn?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how can I make myself &lt;strong&gt;not to go down the wrong path&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and how can I avoid stumbling blocks and feel better?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clickable key points: [&lt;a href=&quot;/mindset/2019/12/20/Struggling-and-auditing-myself-in-2019.html#1-read-the-fucking-manual-rtfm&quot;&gt;rtfm&lt;/a&gt;,
          &lt;a href=&quot;/mindset/2019/12/20/Struggling-and-auditing-myself-in-2019.html#2-no-rushing&quot;&gt;asking-why&lt;/a&gt;,
          &lt;a href=&quot;/mindset/2019/12/20/Struggling-and-auditing-myself-in-2019.html#3-focus-on-fancy-job-titles&quot;&gt;fancy-title&lt;/a&gt;,
          &lt;a href=&quot;/mindset/2019/12/20/Struggling-and-auditing-myself-in-2019.html#4-stick-in-the-mud&quot;&gt;stick-in-the-mud&lt;/a&gt;,
          &lt;a href=&quot;/mindset/2019/12/20/Struggling-and-auditing-myself-in-2019.html#5-fearfulness&quot;&gt;fearfulness&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--description--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-read-the-fucking-manual-rtfm&quot;&gt;1. &lt;strong&gt;READ THE FUCKING MANUAL RTFM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cannot solve issues, cannot understand what’s going on at this infra component&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stuck with ambiguous logs, cannot finding rootcause, only do dirty workarounds…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stuck &amp;amp; feel tired &lt;strong&gt;because having nothing to do next&lt;/strong&gt;. The common sense is when arriving at home, out of business hours, I still spend my time to continue investigating. &lt;strong&gt;Kind of pointless works&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s hard to say how can I survive, but I can confirm that mostly it’s because of not spending time for reading documents. Instead of continue working &amp;amp; step towards the unknown, I re-audit myself and found some important things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Docs are not written for fun&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s all about knowledge &amp;amp; guidelines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lack of knowledge and information will lead to nowhere.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spend time for &lt;strong&gt;reading docs attentively&lt;/strong&gt; is a must, for understanding all things clearly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t wait for collecting knowledge until facing issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strong knowledge base for making decisions is always better than unreasonable assumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-no-rushing&quot;&gt;2. &lt;strong&gt;NO RUSHING&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case is after spending one working week entirely for a task with high sense of concentration, assume that my commitments will be good, mostly finish before the fucking deadline, ready for deploying &amp;amp; delivering to end-user, then… &lt;strong&gt;everything after that is nonreliable&lt;/strong&gt;, unexpected, breakable and not important anymore. &lt;strong&gt;Outcome = Zero&lt;/strong&gt;. Why? Why the fuck changes &amp;amp; happens? No, everything is fine, everything is normal and on track with persistency requirements. Issue here is &lt;strong&gt;not clearly knowing goal&lt;/strong&gt; from the outset, because of &lt;strong&gt;jumping to working immediately without any WHY&lt;/strong&gt;, without any concerns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;without any self-researching and wonder why do I need it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why do I need to build it in that way, do I have any better ways?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do I know exactly what they really want? (product owner, customers, end-user)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does my solution fit with end-user problem?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does my solution speed $$ less than the budget or overestimating?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes &lt;strong&gt;just do it&lt;/strong&gt; is common sense, it’s not wrong, because somehow I cannot spend time for understanding before doing. But not everything needs to be done immediately, no rushing. More multi-dimensional perspective could make a positive impact and lead to the right implementation, it seems to be better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-focus-on-fancy-job-titles&quot;&gt;3. &lt;strong&gt;FOCUS ON FANCY JOB TITLES&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was impressed by engineers with &lt;strong&gt;fancy&lt;/strong&gt; title, something like: waooo, he’s too young but having senior levels, how can I &lt;strong&gt;do like this&lt;/strong&gt;? Looking at senior teammates, this kind of question always stuck in my mind for suck a long time, how can I reach to principal level, How can I write and share technical docs/blog-posts that having extremely deep &amp;amp; intense knowledge, How can I have such reputations on stackoverflow as his own, in many times, I consoled myself that because of senior/principal titles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is: concern, wonder and set goal to reach to higher levels is suck. Consoling is suck too. &lt;strong&gt;If nothing changes, nothing changes&lt;/strong&gt;. Thinking too much is mostly a waste of time. By start working on solving hard problems that I scared before, by taking effort to solve unanswered questions or providing better answers on SO, I feel more energetic and well… at least I did something instead of always asking. It all begins with that first stepping up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/so-reputation.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; title=&quot;Stackoverflow Reputation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the other side, otherwise, collecting a ton of metrics on worloads from engineer is &lt;strong&gt;good for management board&lt;/strong&gt;. It supports us to have a clear and fair making decision on separating levels of Devops/SRE engineer, for adapting and building structures of benefit also with responsibility. Increasing level means &lt;strong&gt;increasing salary/benefit&lt;/strong&gt; based on logged metrics &amp;amp; achievements are totally make sense. It’s fine. I do not disagree 100% about evaluation, because recently by having a chance to work on Devops/SRE evaluation report, I found it really useful to determine the situation, to know what I really need to achieve higher level. But so far, it’s only a checklist, a reference after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-stick-in-the-mud&quot;&gt;4. &lt;strong&gt;STICK-IN-THE-MUD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My real cases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stick with handling AWS on web console clicking, using only EC2 &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;t2.xxxx&lt;/code&gt; type &lt;strong&gt;for years&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;solve perf issues on linux with &lt;strong&gt;fixed viewpoint&lt;/strong&gt;, follow up with templated steps. Feel great when receiving outputs &lt;strong&gt;as expected&lt;/strong&gt;. Kind of &lt;strong&gt;micro skilled works&lt;/strong&gt;, thanks for practicing &amp;amp; developing during a long time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bring experiences on old environment/company, &lt;strong&gt;apply for new place&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;apply &lt;strong&gt;learned techniques&lt;/strong&gt;:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;BAREMETAL-base&lt;/code&gt; for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;VM-based&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;VM-based&lt;/code&gt; for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CONTAINER-based&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;determine that there is &lt;strong&gt;nothing to do&lt;/strong&gt; with this infrastructure this week, because &lt;strong&gt;don’t know what to do next&lt;/strong&gt;, or already did anything.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;… and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m the guy who did all cases as above, &lt;strong&gt;sometimes I feel proud of myself&lt;/strong&gt;, not because of any success I’ve achieved, but because I can &lt;strong&gt;see myself growing up&lt;/strong&gt;, learn, practice and then apply. OK. Nothing wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The illiterate of the 21st century will not be those who cannot read and write, but those who cannot learn, unlearn, and relearn.” – Alvin Toffler&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is feeling good on micro skilled works is suck. There is always something needs to do, &lt;strong&gt;there is always a better way of doing things&lt;/strong&gt;, for enhancing, improving. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/nokia-ceo-ended-his-speech-saying-we-didnt-do-anything-rahul-gupta/&quot;&gt;Like Nokia&lt;/a&gt;: “we didn’t do anything wrong, but somehow, we lost”. Live today in the same state as yesterday does not mean the same, it means lagging behind others. Because &lt;strong&gt;nothing can take the place of persistence&lt;/strong&gt;. Any good thing can be wrong in different situations, not suitable anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hard thing right here is not about learning, it’s about how to detect &amp;amp; know &lt;strong&gt;what can be unlearned&lt;/strong&gt;, what can be re-thinking, &lt;strong&gt;rework&lt;/strong&gt;. Cannot unlearn, struggle with change, difficult to adapt will lead to fucked up. The world is descending into chaos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solutions (hard-to-do)&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when having a chance to add more steps on the old deployment that was built for 6 months ago ==&amp;gt; work on adding new steps first ==&amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;audit entire flow&lt;/strong&gt; ==&amp;gt; then adding some &lt;strong&gt;refactoring instead of leaving it&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when operating an existing infra, the goal is not only cover the uptime of this but also &lt;strong&gt;cover &amp;amp; collect feedback/disadvantage to make it evolve&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;… and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;==&amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;Utilizing&lt;/strong&gt; every chance, every opportunity for &lt;strong&gt;seeking new challenges&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-fearfulness&quot;&gt;5. &lt;strong&gt;FEARFULNESS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know reading docs is good for myself, expand my knowledge base. I know that seeking challenges will help me grow up. I know that doing hard things will achieving high output &amp;amp; have big impact, but somehow I still refuse to do. &lt;strong&gt;I know, but I don’t do.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is always a reason behind everything:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not everything is necessary [tentatively accept]
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Out of scope, just don’t care, stop putting efforts, ask talents when needed.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Closely related, but priority &amp;amp; situation define what &amp;amp; when I will spend time reading &amp;amp; learning.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Laziness, idleness from myself. FML. I have no solution at this time. [tentatively accept]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;color:red;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fucking fearfulness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;fear of doing hard things, afraid of hard stuff, fear because that technical point is too hard to learn&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;fear because it’s edge case, fear &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;/mindset/2019/12/20/Struggling-and-auditing-myself-in-2019.html#4-stick-in-the-mud&quot;&gt;struggle with changes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;fear when working with legacy/unknow things, fear of doing it wrong, making mistakes, fear of receiving bad feedbacks from others&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;feel scared of being not good enough for new challenges, new upcoming things&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, fear is my close friend. Sometimes, I surprise myself that I fear more things than I think.
So how can I survive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Until &lt;strong&gt;there is nobody for delegating&lt;/strong&gt; anymore. It’s becoming a &lt;strong&gt;must thing&lt;/strong&gt; to do. &lt;strong&gt;No one can help me&lt;/strong&gt; do this anymore, I need to do this by myself.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Until I found &lt;a style=&quot;color:red;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;myself unable to accept fucking myself&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; anymore. I feel sad because I missed many good opportunities to make it happens. Set goals 3 months ago, but have done nothing. Because I &lt;strong&gt;realize that I cannot wait&lt;/strong&gt;, cannot ignore hard things anymore.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Until I’m in the zone. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=In%20The%20Zone&quot;&gt;In the zone&lt;/a&gt; means implies increased focus and attention which allow for higher levels of performance, your potential becomes more than what it is and anything around you becomes phased out seemingly a place where you can’t be stopped or touched. &lt;a href=&quot;/mindset/2017/03/12/habit-time-management.html&quot;&gt;Work more when you’re in the zone&lt;/a&gt;. Relax when you’re not. By utilizing in the zone, &lt;a style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“eager” is something more than “fear”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing new under the sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I still wanna audit &amp;amp; write for myself, not about nothing new, it’s about I wanna come to the end of the road of myself to see what it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references--read-more&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;REFERENCES &amp;amp; READ MORE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hvaonline.net/hvaonline/posts/list/0/42715.hva&quot;&gt;Chín thói quen tệ hại cần loại bỏ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vnhacker.blogspot.com/2012/02/de-hoac-ung.html&quot;&gt;Dễ hoặc đúng&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vnhacker.blogspot.com/2017/04/thap-thanh-cong.html&quot;&gt;Tháp thành công&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some mindsets on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vnhacker.blogspot.com/2012/05/lam-toan-thong-tin-thi-hoc-gi.html&quot;&gt;Làm an toàn thông tin thì học gì&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.tracelog.in/mindset/2019/12/20/Struggling-and-auditing-myself-in-2019.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.tracelog.in/mindset/2019/12/20/Struggling-and-auditing-myself-in-2019.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>mindset</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes on CPDOS attack CDN</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Sending malicious HTTP requests (including overside header, meta char, method override header) to CDNs endpoint 
--&amp;gt; these kind of requests are not detected by caching system, are processed by intermediate CDN caching system 
--&amp;gt; then forward to the origin server 
--&amp;gt; origin return server-generated error page 
--&amp;gt; CDN stored error page on edge 
--&amp;gt; CDN serves the same error for normal requests from end-user
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Main impact: AWS Cloudfront (&lt;strong&gt;FIXED&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--description--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/CPDoS.png&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; title=&quot;CPDOS attack CDN&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Site: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cpdos.org&quot;&gt;https://cpdos.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paper: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cpdos.org/paper/Your_Cache_Has_Fallen__Cache_Poisoned_Denial_of_Service_Attack__Preprint_.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reported to HTTP implementation vendors and cache providers on February 19, 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.tracelog.in/technical/security/2019/10/23/Notes-on-CPDOS-attack-CDNs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.tracelog.in/technical/security/2019/10/23/Notes-on-CPDOS-attack-CDNs.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>technical</category>
        
        <category>security</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wildcardfuck</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/asterisk-de.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; title=&quot;Wildcardfuck&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--description--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/asterisk-ch.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; title=&quot;Wildcardfuck&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/asterisk-at.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; title=&quot;Wildcardfuck&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;root-cause&quot;&gt;Root cause&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is no fucking rootcause in these cases.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s lack of knowledge of the guy who did these configurations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’re assuming that you do it right and you know it clearly&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;but you never check&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;learn and understand&lt;/strong&gt; it in the right way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;knowledge-base&quot;&gt;Knowledge base&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Character &lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt;  is &lt;strong&gt;Asterisk&lt;/strong&gt;. A wildcard DNS record is a record in a DNS zone that will match requests for non-existent domain names. A wildcard DNS record is specified by using a &lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt; as the leftmost label (part) of a domain name, e.g. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*.example.com&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wildcards in the DNS are &lt;strong&gt;much more limited&lt;/strong&gt; than other wildcard characters used in other computer systems. &lt;strong&gt;Asterisks at other places in the domain will not work as a wildcard&lt;/strong&gt;, so neither &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*abc.example.com&lt;/code&gt; nor &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;abc.*.example.com&lt;/code&gt; work as wildcard DNS records&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;using-an-asterisk--in-aws-route53-hosted-zones-and-records&quot;&gt;Using an Asterisk (*) in AWS Route53 Hosted Zones and Records&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;You can create hosted zones and records that include &lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt; in the name.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Hosted Zones&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You can’t include an &lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt; in the leftmost label in a domain name. For example, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*.example.com&lt;/code&gt; is not allowed.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you include &lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt; in other positions, DNS treats it as an &lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt; character (&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ASCII 42&lt;/code&gt;), not as a wildcard.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Records&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;DNS treats the &lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt; character either as a wildcard or as the &lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt; character (&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ASCII 42&lt;/code&gt;), depending on where it appears in the name. Note the following restrictions on using &lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt; as a wildcard in the name of a record:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt; must replace the leftmost label in a domain name, for example, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*.example.com&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*.acme.example.com&lt;/code&gt;. If you include &lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt; in any other position, such as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;prod.*.example.com&lt;/code&gt;, DNS treats it as an &lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt; character (&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ASCII 42&lt;/code&gt;), not as a wildcard.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt; must replace the entire label. For example, you can’t specify &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*prod.example.com&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;prod*.example.com&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Specific domain names take precedence. For example, if you create records for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*.example.com&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;acme.example.com&lt;/code&gt;, Route 53 always responds to DNS queries for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;acme.example.com&lt;/code&gt; with the values in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;acme.example.com&lt;/code&gt; record.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt; applies to DNS queries for the subdomain level that includes the asterisk, and all the subdomains of that subdomain. For example, if you create a record named &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*.example.com&lt;/code&gt;, Route 53 uses the values in that record to respond to DNS queries for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;zenith.example.com&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;acme.zenith.example.com&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pinnacle.acme.zenith.example.com&lt;/code&gt; (if there are no records that have those names).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wildcard_DNS_record&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wildcard_DNS_record&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4592#page-6&quot;&gt;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4592#page-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/Route53/latest/DeveloperGuide/DomainNameFormat.html#domain-name-format-asterisk&quot;&gt;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/Route53/latest/DeveloperGuide/DomainNameFormat.html#domain-name-format-asterisk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.tracelog.in/whatthefuck/2019/09/18/Wildcardfuck.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.tracelog.in/whatthefuck/2019/09/18/Wildcardfuck.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>whatthefuck</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Idempotence when extending AWS security group rules in Terraform</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Terraform acts so weird when mixing up between &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aws_security_group&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aws_security_group_rule&lt;/code&gt; in extending AWS security group rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context:&lt;/strong&gt; that leads to not idempotent for each apply (without changing anything in IaC)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create one security group using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aws_security_group&lt;/code&gt; with some predefined inlines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extending more rules (rows) in that secgroup by using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aws_security_group_rule&lt;/code&gt; to add more discrete rules&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At each time executing &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;terraform plan/apply&lt;/code&gt;, terraform re-creates rules lead to fcked up idempotent of result.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sample code at:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DO NOT USE - &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/raw/aws-secgroup-not-idempotence.tf&quot;&gt;aws-secgroup-not-idempotence.tf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;BEST PRACTICE - &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/raw/aws-secgroup-best-practice-idempotence.tf&quot;&gt;aws-secgroup-best-practice-idempotence.tf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!--description--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#a-knowledge-base&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-a-knowledge-base&quot;&gt;A. Knowledge base&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#b-best-practices&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-b-best-practices&quot;&gt;B. Best practices&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#confident-clear--well-configured&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-confident-clear--well-configured&quot;&gt;Confident, clear &amp;amp; well configured&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#extendable-plugable-anywhere-later&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-extendable-plugable-anywhere-later&quot;&gt;Extendable, plugable anywhere later&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#c-issue-links--references&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-c-issue-links--references&quot;&gt;C. Issue links &amp;amp; References&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-knowledge-base&quot;&gt;A. Knowledge base&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For defining AWS secgroup in terraform, we have 2 main ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;inline&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aws_security_group&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Predefined all rules using inline
resource &quot;aws_security_group&quot; &quot;default&quot; {
  name        = &quot;default&quot;
  vpc_id      = &quot;xxxxx&quot;

  ingress {
    from_port   = 22
    to_port     = 22
    protocol    = &quot;tcp&quot;
    description = &quot;Predefined Whitelist &quot;
    cidr_blocks = &quot;${var.whitelist_ips}&quot;
  }

  egress {
    from_port   = 0
    to_port     = 0
    protocol    = &quot;-1&quot;
    cidr_blocks = [&quot;0.0.0.0/0&quot;]
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;discrete&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aws_security_group_rule&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Discrete rules
resource &quot;aws_security_group_rule&quot; &quot;extending_default&quot; {
  type              = &quot;ingress&quot;
  from_port         = 22
  to_port           = 22
  protocol          = &quot;tcp&quot;
  cidr_blocks       = [&quot;1.1.1.1/32&quot;]
  security_group_id = &quot;${aws_security_group.default.id}&quot;
  description       = &quot;VPN&quot;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we streamline one method when configuring, everything is fine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One method using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aws_security_group&lt;/code&gt; and all rules are defined as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;inline&lt;/code&gt; ==&amp;gt;  &lt;strong&gt;PERFECT&lt;/strong&gt; but hard to extended whenever you wanna fetch that security group ID from another place.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One method using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aws_security_group&lt;/code&gt; without any inline, and use each &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aws_security_group_rule&lt;/code&gt; for defining rules ==&amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;PERFECT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we mixed up by predefined inline in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aws_security_group&lt;/code&gt; then continue extending by discrete more rules in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aws_security_group_rule&lt;/code&gt; ==&amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;FCKED UP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE on Security Groups and Security Group Rules:&lt;/strong&gt; Terraform currently provides both a standalone Security Group Rule resource (a single &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ingress&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;egress&lt;/code&gt; rule), and a Security Group resource with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ingress&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;egress&lt;/code&gt; rules &lt;strong&gt;defined in-line&lt;/strong&gt;. At this time you &lt;strong&gt;cannot use&lt;/strong&gt; a Security Group with in-line rules in conjunction with any Security Group Rule resources. Doing so will cause a conflict of rule settings and will overwrite rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.terraform.io/docs/providers/aws/r/security_group.html&quot;&gt;terraform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;b-best-practices&quot;&gt;B. Best practices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;confident-clear--well-configured&quot;&gt;Confident, clear &amp;amp; well configured&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;If we’re confident to say that our secgroup is well defined from the first place in mind, init one time, then use in many place and &lt;strong&gt;no need to changes/extend anymore&lt;/strong&gt; in the future, so go head with configuring entire segroup &amp;amp; rule in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aws_security_group&lt;/code&gt; by inline&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;extendable-plugable-anywhere-later&quot;&gt;Extendable, plugable anywhere later&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;If we’re working on one secgroup which is not well-defined in the first time, need extended and plug in/out rules in another place, go head with configuring core skeletion of secgroup using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aws_security_group&lt;/code&gt; without any rules, then plug in rule by rule with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;aws_security_group_rule&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Create secgroup skeleton without any inline
resource &quot;aws_security_group&quot; &quot;default_http&quot; {
  name        = &quot;default-http&quot;
  vpc_id      = &quot;xxxxx&quot;
}

# Then define rules for this above secgroup
resource &quot;aws_security_group_rule&quot; &quot;default_http_ingress&quot; {
  type             = &quot;ingress&quot;
  from_port        = 80
  to_port          = 80
  protocol         = &quot;tcp&quot;
  description      = &quot;Worldwide&quot;
  cidr_blocks      = [&quot;0.0.0.0/0&quot;]
  security_group_id = aws_security_group.default_http.id
}

resource &quot;aws_security_group_rule&quot; &quot;default_https_ingress&quot; {
  type             = &quot;ingress&quot;
  from_port        = 443
  to_port          = 443
  protocol         = &quot;tcp&quot;
  description      = &quot;Worldwide&quot;
  cidr_blocks      = [&quot;0.0.0.0/0&quot;]
  security_group_id = aws_security_group.default_http.id
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;c-issue-links--references&quot;&gt;C. Issue links &amp;amp; References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cavaliercoder.com/blog/inline-vs-discrete-security-groups-in-terraform.html&quot;&gt;http://cavaliercoder.com/blog/inline-vs-discrete-security-groups-in-terraform.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hashicorp/terraform/issues/11011&quot;&gt;https://github.com/hashicorp/terraform/issues/11011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/terraform-providers/terraform-provider-aws/issues/742&quot;&gt;https://github.com/terraform-providers/terraform-provider-aws/issues/742&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hashicorp/terraform/issues/14124&quot;&gt;https://github.com/hashicorp/terraform/issues/14124&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.tracelog.in/technical/2019/08/13/Idempotence-when-extending-AWS-security-group-rules-in-Terraform.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.tracelog.in/technical/2019/08/13/Idempotence-when-extending-AWS-security-group-rules-in-Terraform.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>technical</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The art of on-call duty</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Being on-call means working/fixing live issues under high pressure and almost during midnight and/or weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Taking strong responsibility&lt;/strong&gt; for what we work, for what we did, for what we build&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Uptime is an important metric, also critical to the success of our production.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If our product is down, &lt;strong&gt;we acutely feel our customer’s pain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being on-call duty means we can &lt;strong&gt;learn a lot from it&lt;/strong&gt;, for both technical knowledge &amp;amp; growing mindset.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Must get high paid for each on-call duty shift, because of stressful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/NTur7XlVDUdqM&quot; width=&quot;768&quot; height=&quot;419&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;!--description--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-art-of-on-call-duty&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-the-art-of-on-call-duty&quot;&gt;THE ART OF ON-CALL DUTY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#standard-flow-for-on-call-duty-life-cycle&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-standard-flow-for-on-call-duty-life-cycle&quot;&gt;STANDARD FLOW FOR ON-CALL DUTY LIFE CYCLE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#root-cause&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-root-cause&quot;&gt;ROOT CAUSE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#reference&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-reference&quot;&gt;REFERENCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-art-of-on-call-duty&quot;&gt;THE ART OF ON-CALL DUTY&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Important points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep production services reliable and available&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Must have one of many dedicated teams of SREs that always take responsibility for the performance and reliability, also must have a &lt;strong&gt;strong background&lt;/strong&gt; of system/infra/network and software development (because maybe need to inspect each line of code)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you know you might get woken up in the middle of the night if there is a problem, you become more careful building infra, implementing components and testing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Troubleshooting the system forces you to get a good understanding of &lt;strong&gt;how it all works&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being on-call means we always facing with these internal issues like:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;troubleshooting tools aren’t as good as they should be&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;false alarms, unreliable alarms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;logs without useful information&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;have no way to backup/restore&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;=&amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;Improve our mindset&lt;/strong&gt; for making alerting/monitoring/logging system better during live issues, driving improvements at every part of entire our system&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;standard-flow-for-on-call-duty-life-cycle&quot;&gt;STANDARD FLOW FOR ON-CALL DUTY LIFE CYCLE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build&lt;/strong&gt;: init monitoring &amp;amp; logging system that help us detect live failures before most customers notice a problem, set up a reliable alerting system (pagerduty) to make sure we can receive alerts immediately&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prepare&lt;/strong&gt;: rotating SRE team member by shift to make sure we always have at least one guy to take care production anytime, also covered with always ready machine/LTE/phone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Triage&lt;/strong&gt;: acknowledge (ack) on alerts whenever you can, determine the urgency of the problem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fix&lt;/strong&gt;: take whatever actions are necessary in order to resolve the issue immediately and get production back to normal, including implement hotfix or even rollback to the last working version.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Report&lt;/strong&gt;: after fixing incident, need to file ticket/report for logging which issues, what we did for solving, file a JIRA ticket to keep a track and push more and more details into this, writing a postmortem (incident postmortem is an excellent framework for learning from incidents and turning problems into progress)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow-up &amp;amp; Improvement&lt;/strong&gt;: fixed issues &amp;amp; logged into specific tickets do not mean we’re done with that, not yet. We must &lt;strong&gt;take action to follow-up after incident&lt;/strong&gt;, how to &lt;strong&gt;prevent these issues in the future&lt;/strong&gt;, improve sense of alerting, how can we backup/restore/rollback, how to make alarm more &lt;strong&gt;precise, responsive, and sensitive&lt;/strong&gt;. At every step of follow-up/improvement, must write them down to central documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;root-cause&quot;&gt;ROOT CAUSE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If we only fix the symptoms (what we see on the surface), the problem will almost certainly return, and need fixing over, and over again&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So the Root cause means:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What has caused the incident?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What’s the reason the system failed the way it did?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What’s initiating cause that led to an outage or degradation in performance&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If we know and identify the root cause, action can be taken to fix issues permanently&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a technical way, root cause of live issues can be separated into 3 groups&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Changes in the last deployment&lt;/strong&gt;: changes in codebase, changes in configurations, but not be tested carefully or not aware of hidden failures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exist at scale&lt;/strong&gt;: during high traffic, during unexpected traffic, bottle-neck or facing limitations of some important components&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3rd party issue&lt;/strong&gt;: hardware failure, provider/ISP failure, unreliable networking, 3rd API issues,…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;REFERENCE&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://henrikwarne.com/2018/12/03/developer-on-call/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://www.intercom.com/blog/rapid-response-how-we-developed-an-on-call-team-at-intercom/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://response.pagerduty.com/oncall/being_oncall/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://landing.google.com/sre/sre-book/chapters/being-on-call/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://www.atlassian.com/blog/statuspage/incident-postmortem-writing-tips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.tracelog.in/mindset/2019/03/23/The-art-of-on-call-duty.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.tracelog.in/mindset/2019/03/23/The-art-of-on-call-duty.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>mindset</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jenkinsfuck</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/jenkins-oops.webp&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; title=&quot;EatWhatYouKill&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--description--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Mar 01, 2019 11:19:14 AM org.eclipse.jetty.server.handler.ContextHandler$Context log
WARNING: Error while serving https://ci.tools.xxxxxx.io/job/live-xxxxxx/27/logText/progressiveHtml
java.lang.reflect.InvocationTargetException
    at org.kohsuke.stapler.Function$MethodFunction.invoke(Function.java:347)
    ...
    ...
    at org.eclipse.jetty.io.ChannelEndPoint$2.run(ChannelEndPoint.java:118)
    at org.eclipse.jetty.util.thread.strategy.EatWhatYouKill.runTask(EatWhatYouKill.java:333)
    at org.eclipse.jetty.util.thread.strategy.EatWhatYouKill.doProduce(EatWhatYouKill.java:310)
    at org.eclipse.jetty.util.thread.strategy.EatWhatYouKill.tryProduce(EatWhatYouKill.java:168)
    at org.eclipse.jetty.util.thread.strategy.EatWhatYouKill.run(EatWhatYouKill.java:126)
    at org.eclipse.jetty.util.thread.ReservedThreadExecutor$ReservedThread.run(ReservedThreadExecutor.java:366)
    ...
    ...
Caused by: java.lang.NegativeArraySizeException
    at hudson.console.ConsoleNote.readFrom(ConsoleNote.java:241)
    at hudson.console.ConsoleAnnotationOutputStream.eol(ConsoleAnnotationOutputStream.java:109)
    at hudson.console.LineTransformationOutputStream.eol(LineTransformationOutputStream.java:60)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;root-cause&quot;&gt;Root cause&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of log: &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/raw/jenkins-NegativeArraySizeException-error.log&quot;&gt;jenkins-NegativeArraySizeException-error.log&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;NegativeArraySizeException&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;extends&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;RuntimeException&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thrown if an application tries to create an array with negative size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Output of this running job is: too big and spawn too fast &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rarely&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; that reach &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;NegativeArraySize&lt;/code&gt; during entire log workflow from&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ConsoleNote &amp;gt; ConsoleAnnotationOutputStream &amp;gt; FileLogStorage &amp;gt; ProxyOutputStream&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to doProgressText and until doProgressiveHtml&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EatWhatYouKill&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t panic, just wait, let them come then let them go. Wait until this fucking job DONE. Then issuse will….gone&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.tracelog.in/whatthefuck/2019/03/01/Jenkinsfuck.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.tracelog.in/whatthefuck/2019/03/01/Jenkinsfuck.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>whatthefuck</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mountfuck</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/wrong-mount-in-es.webp&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot; title=&quot;Entire fucking dir in fuckin /var/lib/elasticsearch&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--description--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;root-cause&quot;&gt;Root cause&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/AWSEC2/latest/UserGuide/nvme-ebs-volumes.html&quot;&gt;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/AWSEC2/latest/UserGuide/nvme-ebs-volumes.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;EBS uses single-root I/O virtualization (SR-IOV) to provide volume attachments on Nitro-based instances using the NVMe specification. 
These devices rely on standard NVMe drivers on the operating system. 
These drivers typically discover attached devices by scanning the PCI bus during instance boot, and create device nodes based on the order in which the devices respond, not on how the devices are specified in the block device mapping. 
In Linux, NVMe device names follow the pattern /dev/nvme&amp;lt;x&amp;gt;n&amp;lt;y&amp;gt;, where &amp;lt;x&amp;gt; is the enumeration order, and, for EBS, &amp;lt;y&amp;gt; is 1. 
Occasionally, devices can respond to discovery in a different order in subsequent instance starts, which causes the device name to change.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if we use NVMe disk for some new types of AWS EC2, please note that the device name is nearly randomize after each reboot.
It means if we have 2 NVMe disks on one EC2 vm, so we cannot know which device name delegate to which real disk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;/dev/nvme1n1p1
/dev/nvme0n1p1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must config fstab (permanent mount) based on UUID / label like this&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;LABEL=cloudimg-rootfs  /   ext4  defaults,discard  0 0
UUID=&quot;c46cf311-d31b-41ce-bce5-5d8ad0a6b109&quot; /var/lib/elasticsearch ext4 defaults,nofail  0 2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DON’T config based on device name like this fuck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;LABEL=cloudimg-rootfs	/	 ext4	defaults,discard	0 0
/dev/nvme1n1p1 /var/lib/elasticsearch ext4 defaults,nofail  0 2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.tracelog.in/whatthefuck/2019/01/23/Mountfuck.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.tracelog.in/whatthefuck/2019/01/23/Mountfuck.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>whatthefuck</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Some meaningful thoughts for entire 2018</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a post for reminding these learned points, thinkings, ideas, mindsets about how to do and live better in 2018, only for myself. I logged because I scare that I will forget and go wrong or do the same mistake ever and ever again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time is a &lt;strong&gt;fixed&lt;/strong&gt; and the most important resource, if taking care too much about non-sense things, &lt;strong&gt;will have no time&lt;/strong&gt; for really right and important things in your life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run, think and &lt;strong&gt;improve continuously whatever&lt;/strong&gt;, even small/big things everyday. Live today in the same state as yesterday does not mean the same, it means &lt;strong&gt;lagging behind others&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Write down, well documented, or take note on somewhere because of &lt;strong&gt;forgetting process&lt;/strong&gt; in the human brain, but make sure &lt;strong&gt;never forget mindsets&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;core thinking techniques&lt;/strong&gt; (like critical thinking, SWOT analysis,…). Details can forget, but cores must be in brain, seriously.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Must know &lt;strong&gt;why you do what you do?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Should have private time for yourself (every week), no smartphone, no laptop, no people, just you and think about the past week or doing meditation for training attention and awareness, achieve a mentally clear and emotionally calm state.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!--description--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;there-are-only-2-basic-types-of-action&quot;&gt;There are only 2 basic types of action:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One: you can totally control this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two: you be forced to do regardless of you hate or refuse to do, don’t care, let them come then let them go.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to note and share about &lt;strong&gt;the first one&lt;/strong&gt;. So you can control actions, think about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making decision for doing the right thing at right time for &lt;strong&gt;gaining highest value&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on working scoped things during 8hrs working day, only for increasing quality of your company products, &lt;strong&gt;ignore non-sense things&lt;/strong&gt; (including fuckers and dirty ones, &lt;strong&gt;who the fuck cares&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do one thing, get it done first (minimum viable), take a rest then get back to work on improvement, check every case, every reason. &lt;strong&gt;DROP OTHERS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t fucking any care about trash, shitty, fuckers, stupid, nonsense, not related to you. &lt;strong&gt;IGNORE.IGNORE.IGNORE.&lt;/strong&gt; is the key.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Time is a fixed and the most important resource,
if taking care too much about non-sense things, 
will have no time for really right and important things in your life.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s all about trade-offs and makes the right decisions.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.tracelog.in/mindset/2019/01/08/Some-meaningful-thoughts-for-entire-2018.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.tracelog.in/mindset/2019/01/08/Some-meaningful-thoughts-for-entire-2018.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>mindset</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Critical vulnerability on policykit of systemd</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[CVE-2018-19788]&lt;/strong&gt;: A flaw was found in PolicyKit (aka &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;polkit 0.115&lt;/code&gt;) that allows a user with a uid greater than &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;INT_MAX&lt;/code&gt; to successfully execute any &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;systemctl&lt;/code&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/systemd/systemd/issues/11026&quot;&gt;https://github.com/systemd/systemd/issues/11026&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/freedesktop/polkit/blob/8c1bc8a/src/programs/pkttyagent.c#L156&quot;&gt;https://github.com/freedesktop/polkit/blob/8c1bc8a/src/programs/pkttyagent.c#L156&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/polkit/polkit/issues/74&quot;&gt;https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/polkit/polkit/issues/74&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find out more about CVE-2018-19788 from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2018-19788&quot;&gt;MITRE CVE&lt;/a&gt; dictionary and &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.nvd.nist.gov/view/vuln/detail?vulnId=CVE-2018-19788&quot;&gt;NIST NVD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/CVE-2018-19788.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--description--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;demo&quot;&gt;DEMO&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;root@ahihi:~# &lt;/span&gt;useradd -u 4000000000 wtf
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;root@ahihi:~# &lt;/span&gt;su - wtf
No directory, logging &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;in &lt;/span&gt;with &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;HOME&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;/

&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;whoami
wtf
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;id
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;uid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;4000000000&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;wtf&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;gid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;1002&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;wtf&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;groups&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;1002&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;wtf&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;systemctl stop sshd.service

&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;process:22860&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;: GLib-GObject-WARNING &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;**&lt;/span&gt;: value &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;-294967296&quot;&lt;/span&gt; of &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'gint'&lt;/span&gt; is invalid or out of range &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for &lt;/span&gt;property &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'uid'&lt;/span&gt; of &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'gint'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;**&lt;/span&gt;
ERROR:pkttyagent.c:175:main: assertion failed: &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;polkit_unix_process_get_uid &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;POLKIT_UNIX_PROCESS &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;subject&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &amp;gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; 0&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;root@ahihi:~# &lt;/span&gt;systemctl status sshd.service
...
Dec 05 15:38:39 ahihi systemd[1]: Stopping OpenBSD Secure Shell server...
Dec 05 15:38:39 ahihi systemd[1]: Stopped OpenBSD Secure Shell server.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.tracelog.in/technical/security/2018/12/05/Critial-vulnerability-on-policykit-of-systemd.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.tracelog.in/technical/security/2018/12/05/Critial-vulnerability-on-policykit-of-systemd.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>technical</category>
        
        <category>security</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Debian on android shell</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goal&lt;/strong&gt;: I had one old Android phone, with broken touching/gesture layer. One day, I found it on a dirty old place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wonder how can I make it better with more usability.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can I make it work exactly as I needed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can I transform this old phone to a super tiny linux machine with interactive shell?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Device: xiaomi Mi4W LTE, android 6.0.1 MMB29M
Specs: Qualcomm MSM8974PRO-AC Quad-core max 2.5GHz, 3.00 GB memory, 16GB disk
Kernel: 3.4.0-gf4b741d-00690-gc8911e
Arch: armv7l
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/android-shell.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--description--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#a-knowledge-base&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-a-knowledge-base&quot;&gt;A. Knowledge base&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#b-hacking--practicing-zone&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-b-hacking--practicing-zone&quot;&gt;B. Hacking / Practicing zone&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1-install-adb-and-fastboot-tools-on-mac&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-1-install-adb-and-fastboot-tools-on-mac&quot;&gt;1. Install adb and fastboot tools on mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2-download-then-install-twrp--supersu-on-fastboot&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-2-download-then-install-twrp--supersu-on-fastboot&quot;&gt;2. Download then install twrp &amp;amp; supersu on fastboot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#3-expand-utilities-with-busybox&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-3-expand-utilities-with-busybox&quot;&gt;3. Expand utilities with busybox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#4-config--fix-env-variables-and-configuations&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-4-config--fix-env-variables-and-configuations&quot;&gt;4. Config / fix env variables and configuations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#5-extract-debianimg-from-available-debian-system-not-bsd-os-like-mac&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-5-extract-debianimg-from-available-debian-system-not-bsd-os-like-mac&quot;&gt;5. Extract debian.img from available debian system (not BSD os like Mac)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#6-debootstrapping-debian-into-android-os&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-6-debootstrapping-debian-into-android-os&quot;&gt;6. Debootstrapping debian into android os&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#7-complete-debian-os-with-apt-and-networking&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-7-complete-debian-os-with-apt-and-networking&quot;&gt;7. Complete debian os with apt and networking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#8-performance-benchmarking&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-8-performance-benchmarking&quot;&gt;8. Performance benchmarking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#c-reference&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-c-reference&quot;&gt;C. Reference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-knowledge-base&quot;&gt;A. Knowledge base&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For accessing default android shell, we need &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; tools. For booting operation with custom image, we use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fastboot&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;adb reboot recovery&lt;/code&gt;.
After accessing, with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;twrp&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;supersu&lt;/code&gt; we can grant &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;root&lt;/code&gt; privileges because we need root permission for doing &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mount&lt;/code&gt; filesystem and totally control the whole system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also need &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;busybox&lt;/code&gt; for expanding utilities like editing files by &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;vi&lt;/code&gt;, checking network connection, …
It’s done for controlling android via &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;adb shell&lt;/code&gt;, but currently, linux os on android is designed for mobile, apk applications, everyday carry and easy to use for all kinds of users, also it’s not using any kind of package management like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;apt&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;yum&lt;/code&gt;, I nearly can do nothing on current system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From devops/sre point of view, all I want is pushing/booting a fully &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;linux&lt;/code&gt; os to my android, that’s I can do more things on this, instead of limited android os.
I decided to use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;debian stretch&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;debootrap&lt;/code&gt; for extract custom image and init debian filesystem via &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;chroot&lt;/code&gt; to current android &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sdcard&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;b-hacking--practicing-zone&quot;&gt;B. Hacking / Practicing zone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-install-adb-and-fastboot-tools-on-mac&quot;&gt;1. Install adb and fastboot tools on mac&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mac❯❯ brew cask install android-platform-tools

mac❯❯ adb --version
Android Debug Bridge version 1.0.40
Version 4797878
Installed as /usr/local/bin/adb

mac❯❯ fastboot --version
fastboot version 28.0.0-4797878
Installed as /usr/local/bin/fastboot

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Connect android to mac via usb &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Verify device&lt;/span&gt;

mac❯❯ adb devices -l
List of devices attached
1f703708  device usb:336592896X product:cancro_wc_lte model:MI_4W device:cancro transport_id:13
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-download-then-install-twrp--supersu-on-fastboot&quot;&gt;2. Download then install twrp &amp;amp; supersu on fastboot&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mac❯❯ wget internet.com/SR5-SuperSU-v2.82-SR5-20171001224502.zip ./
mac❯❯ wget internet.com/twrp-3.1.0-0-cancro.img ./
mac❯❯ adb push ./SR5-SuperSU-v2.82-SR5-20171001224502.zip /storage/self/primary/
SR5-SuperSU-v2.82-SR5-20171001224502.zip: 1 file pushed. 5.8 MB/s &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;6882992 bytes &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;in &lt;/span&gt;1.127s&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

mac❯❯ adb reboot bootloader

mac❯❯ fastboot devices
1f703708	fastboot

mac❯❯ fastboot flash recovery ./twrp-3.1.0-0-cancro.img
Sending &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'recovery'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;13682 KB&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;                      OKAY &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;  0.464s]
Writing &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'recovery'&lt;/span&gt;                                 OKAY &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;  0.305s]
Finished. Total &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;time&lt;/span&gt;: 0.772s

mac❯❯ fastboot boot ./twrp-3.1.0-0-cancro.img
Downloading &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'boot.img'&lt;/span&gt;                             OKAY &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;  0.432s]
booting                                            OKAY &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;  0.119s]
Finished. Total &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;time&lt;/span&gt;: 0.560s

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# After booted into TWRP&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Install SR5-SuperSU-v2.82-SR5-20171001224502.zip from TWRP&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Do it on touch screen, or via twrp commandline&lt;/span&gt;

mac❯❯ adb shell 
android❯❯ twrp install /storage/self/primary/SR5-SuperSU-v2.82-SR5-20171001224502.zip
android❯❯ twrp wipe cache
android❯❯ reboot

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Verify root on device&lt;/span&gt;

mac❯❯ adb shell
shell@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;su -
root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# whoami&lt;/span&gt;
root
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-expand-utilities-with-busybox&quot;&gt;3. Expand utilities with busybox&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mac❯❯ wget https://busybox.net/downloads/binaries/1.28.1-defconfig-multiarch/busybox-armv7l
mac❯❯ adb push busybox-armv7l /data/local/tmp
busybox-armv7l: 1 file pushed. 3.8 MB/s &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;1079156 bytes &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;in &lt;/span&gt;0.270s&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

mac❯❯ adb shell
shell@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;su -
root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# mkdir /data/busybox&lt;/span&gt;
root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# move /data/local/tmp/busybox-armv7l /data/busybox&lt;/span&gt;
root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# cd /data/busybox&lt;/span&gt;
root@cancro:/data/busybox &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# ls -l&lt;/span&gt;
-rwxrwxrwx shell    shell     1079156 2018-02-15 20:47 busybox-armv7l
root@cancro:/data/busybox &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# ./busybox-armv7l --install ./&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Use ls of busybox &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# instead of current ls on android&lt;/span&gt;

root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# which ls&lt;/span&gt;
/system/bin/ls

root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# export PATH=/data/busybox:$PATH&lt;/span&gt;
root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# which ls&lt;/span&gt;
/data/busybox/ls
root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# which vi&lt;/span&gt;
/data/busybox/vi
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-config--fix-env-variables-and-configuations&quot;&gt;4. Config / fix env variables and configuations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Choose one: (for security mount /system back to RO when finished)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Mount system RW: mount -o rw,remount /system&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Mount system RO: mount -o ro,remount /system&lt;/span&gt;

root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# mount -o rw,remount /system&lt;/span&gt;
root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# vi /system/etc/mkshrc&lt;/span&gt;
...
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;export &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;PATH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;/data/busybox:&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$PATH&lt;/span&gt;
...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;when facing with su command like this, we need reconfigure su&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Issue with su command&lt;/span&gt;

shell@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;su
su: must be suid to work properly

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Resolve&lt;/span&gt;

root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# cp /su/bin/su /data/busybox/su&lt;/span&gt;
root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# ls -lh /su/bin/su&lt;/span&gt;
-rwxr-xr-x    1 0        0          73.6K Sep 11 13:49 /su/bin/su
root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# ls -lh /data/busybox/su&lt;/span&gt;
-rwx------    1 0        0          73.6K Sep 11 15:58 /data/busybox/su
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-extract-debianimg-from-available-debian-system-not-bsd-os-like-mac&quot;&gt;5. Extract debian.img from available debian system (not BSD os like Mac)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install debootstrap then bootstrapping debian stretch image for armv7l arch&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;debian❯❯ apt install -y debootstrap debian-archive-keyring debian-ports-archive-keyring
debian❯❯ mkdir debian-armhf
debian❯❯ &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd &lt;/span&gt;debian-armhf/
debian❯❯ dd &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;/dev/zero &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;debian.img &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;bs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;1MiB &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;2000
debian❯❯ mke2fs -F debian.img
debian❯❯ mkdir debian
debian❯❯ mount -o loop debian.img debian
debian❯❯ debootstrap --arch armhf --foreign --verbose stretch debian http://ftp.us.debian.org/debian
debian❯❯ umount debian
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/debootstrap.webp&quot; alt=&quot;large-img&quot; title=&quot;Extract debian filesystem via Debootstrap&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;rsync file debian.img from debian system to mac system, then push this img to android&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mac❯❯ adb push debian.img /sdcard/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-debootstrapping-debian-into-android-os&quot;&gt;6. Debootstrapping debian into android os&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mac❯❯ adb shell

shell@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;su -
root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# mkdir /sdcard/debian-stretch9&lt;/span&gt;
root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# losetup /dev/block/loop99 /sdcard/debian.img&lt;/span&gt;
root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# mount /dev/block/loop99 /sdcard/debian-stretch9&lt;/span&gt;
root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# chroot /sdcard/debian-stretch9 /bin/bash&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;export &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;PATH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;/usr/bin:/usr/sbin:/bin:&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$PATH&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;export &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;TERM&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;linux
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;export &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;HOME&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;/root
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;export &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;USER&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;root
/debootstrap/debootstrap --second-stage

&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;nameserver 8.8.8.8&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; /etc/resolv.conf
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;127.0.0.1 localhost&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;gt; /etc/hosts
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;exit

&lt;/span&gt;mac❯❯ adb shell
shell@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;su -
root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# chroot /sdcard/debian-stretch9 /bin/su - root&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;root@localhost:~# &lt;/span&gt;whoami &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#should be root&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;root@localhost:~# &lt;/span&gt;cat /etc/debian_version &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#9.5&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;7-complete-debian-os-with-apt-and-networking&quot;&gt;7. Complete debian os with apt and networking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the first time, I cannot use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ping&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;apt&lt;/code&gt;, because Android uses a special Kernel patch that’s activated with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CONFIG_ANDROID_PARANOID_NETWORK&lt;/code&gt;. 
For adding specific groups, this patch allows network access to system users that belong to certain special groups with hardcoded IDs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mac❯❯ adb shell
shell@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;su -
root@cancro:/ &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# chroot /sdcard/debian-stretch9/ /bin/su - root&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;root@localhost:~# &lt;/span&gt;groupadd -g 3001 aid_bt
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;root@localhost:~# &lt;/span&gt;groupadd -g 3002 aid_bt_net
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;root@localhost:~# &lt;/span&gt;groupadd -g 3003 aid_inet
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;root@localhost:~# &lt;/span&gt;groupadd -g 3004 aid_net_raw
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;root@localhost:~# &lt;/span&gt;groupadd -g 3005 aid_admin
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;root@localhost:~# &lt;/span&gt;usermod -a -G aid_bt,aid_bt_net,aid_inet,aid_net_raw,aid_admin root
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;exit&lt;/span&gt; - relogin

&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;root@localhost:~# &lt;/span&gt;grep -E &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;_apt&quot;&lt;/span&gt; /etc/passwd
_apt:x:104:65534::/nonexistent:/bin/false

&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;root@localhost:~# &lt;/span&gt;usermod -g 3003 _apt
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;root@localhost:~# &lt;/span&gt;grep -E &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;_apt&quot;&lt;/span&gt; /etc/passwd
_apt:x:104:3003::/nonexistent:/bin/false

&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;root@localhost:~# &lt;/span&gt;apt update
Ign:1 http://ftp.de.debian.org/pub/debian stable InRelease
Get:2 http://ftp.de.debian.org/pub/debian stable Release &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;118 kB]
...
Fetched 12.7 MB &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;in &lt;/span&gt;36s &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;351 kB/s&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
Reading package lists... Done
Building dependency tree... Done
All packages are up to date.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;8-performance-benchmarking&quot;&gt;8. Performance benchmarking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…to be continue&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;c-reference&quot;&gt;C. Reference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikitechy.com/technology/how-to-root-and-install-twrp-recovery-on-xiaomi-mi4/&quot;&gt;TWRP fastboot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://android.stackexchange.com/questions/53389/can-i-update-the-adb-shells-environment-variables&quot;&gt;ADB shell environment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://android.stackexchange.com/questions/110927/how-to-mount-system-rewritable-or-read-only-rw-ro&quot;&gt;Mount /system RR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://busybox.net/FAQ.html&quot;&gt;Busybox FAQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cryptojedi.org/misc/nexuss-debian.shtml&quot;&gt;Debian on android&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/36451444/what-can-cause-a-socket-permission-denied-error&quot;&gt;Chroot on android&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.tracelog.in/technical/2018/09/11/Debian-on-android-shell.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.tracelog.in/technical/2018/09/11/Debian-on-android-shell.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>technical</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
